# Curriculum Vitæ— Diego Zamboni

November 15, 2013— short version

### Personal information

Full name: Diego Martín Zamboni

Email: diego@zzamboni.org
Web: http://zzamboni.org/

LinkedIn: http://mx.linkedin.com/in/zzamboni

Twitter: http://twitter.com/zzamboni

#### Introduction

I possess a strong combination of theoretical and practical knowledge in multiple areas of computing that make me able to analyze complex problems and design elegant solutions. I am a team player and a natural leader. I am self-motivated and have excellent communication skills in both Spanish and English, including ample experience in technical writing, teaching and public speaking. I have a strong and rich background, including advanced education, scientific research, practical technical knowledge and customer-facing experience.

## Areas of interest and expertise

Computer security:

Intrusion detection and prevention, operating systems security, network security, software security, secure software development, virtualization and cloud computing security, malware detection and containment.

Other areas:

Virtualization and cloud computing; configuration management; operating system design, implementation and administration; network administration; programming languages; human-computer interfaces.

## Work experience

August 2013 to date: Product Manager at CFEngine AS. I coordinate the discussion and set direction for future development of the CFEngine Design Center and the CFEngine language roadmap.

October 2011 to date: Senior Security Advisor at CFEngine AS. I work as an overall advocate and fanatic for CFEngine, with a special focus on security. I give talks, write articles and blog posts, teach classes, and in general spread the word about CFEngine. I also work on developing and implementing the strategy for CFEngine in security.

October 2010–October 2011: Account Security Officer at HP Enterprise Services Mexico. In this position I was the first point of contact for all security-related issues for five HP enterprise customers in Mexico, some of them with international presence.

November 2009–October 2010: IT Outsourcing Service Delivery Consultant at HP Enterprise Services Mexico. My role was to help customer teams by solving complex problems in customer environments.

October 2001–October 2009: Research staff member at the IBM Zurich Research Laboratory. The focus of my work was in intrusion detection, malware detection and containment, and virtualization security. See *Research activities* for details of research.

August 1995–August 1996: Founder and head of Computer Security Area National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM).

## **Education**

Ph.D. in Computer Science: August 1996–August 2001.

Purdue University, Department of Computer Sciences.

This is a short version. The full version of this document can be found online at http://zzamboni.org/vita.html.

Thesis title: *Using Internal Sensors for Computer Intrusion Detection*.

Advisor: Eugene H. Spafford.

M.S. in Computer Science: August 1996–May 1998.

Purdue University, Department of Computer Sciences.

Advisor: Eugene H. Spafford.

### **Publications (sample)**

Books: Diego Zamboni. Learning CFEngine 3. O'Reilly Media, Inc., March 2012. ISBN

9781449312206. URL http://cf-learn.info/.

Editorial activities: From 2011–2013 I was a member of the Editorial Board for the Computers & Security Journal.

Diego Zamboni and Christopher Kruegel, editors. *Recent Advances in Intrusion Detection: 9th International Symposium, RAID 2006, Hamburg, Germany, September 20-22, 2006, Proceedings (Lecture Notes in Computer Science)*. Springer-Verlag New York, Inc., Secaucus, NJ, USA, 2006.

ISBN 354039723X.

Deborah Frincke, Andreas Wespi, and Diego Zamboni. Guest editorial: From intrusion detection to self-protection. *Computer Networks*, 51(5):1233–1238, 2007. ISSN 1389-1286. URL

http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.comnet.2006.10.004.

Refereed papers: Urko Zurutuza, Roberto Uribeetxeberria, and Diego Zamboni. A data mining approach for analysis of worm activity through automatic signature generation. In *Proceedings of the 1st* 

ACM workshop on AISec (AISec'08), pages 61–70, New York, NY, USA, October 2008. ISBN

978-1-60558-291-7. URL http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1456377.1456394.

Diego Zamboni, James Riordan, and Milton Yates. Boundary detection and containment of local worm infections. In *Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Steps to Reducing Unwanted Traffic on the Internet (SRUTI'07)*. Usenix, June 2007. URL http://www.usenix.org/events/

sruti07/tech/full\_papers/zamboni/zamboni.pdf.

James Riordan, Diego Zamboni, and Yann Duponchel. Building and deploying Billy Goat, a worm-detection system. In *Proceedings of the 18th Annual FIRST Conference*, June 2006.

Florian Kerschbaum, Eugene H. Spafford, and Diego Zamboni. Using internal sensors and embedded detectors for intrusion detection. *Journal of Computer Security*, 10(1,2):23–70, 2002. URL http://iospress.metapress.com/content/rkylmv8hepn2p71d/.

**Certifications** *Foundation Certificate in IT-Service Management* (ITILv2), April 2006.

IBM Micro MBA program, March 2003.

#### Research activities

Selected research projects at IBM:

**Project Phantom:** (2008-2009) Security for VMware virtual environments using virtual machine introspection.

**Code instrumentation for intrusion detection:** (2007) Exploration of code instrumentation and low-level monitoring mechanisms for performing efficient and accurate intrusion detection and prevention.

**Billy Goat:** (2002–2008) An active worm-detection system.

**Router-based Billy Goat:** (2005–2007) An active worm-capture device.

**SOC in a Box:** (2005–2007) Integrated device containing multiple security tools.

**Exorcist:** (2001–2002) Host-based, behavior-based intrusion detection using sequences of system calls.

Ph.D. thesis research:

Utilization of internal sensors and embedded detectors for intrusion detection.

Additional projects: Using autonomous agents for intrusion detection.

Analysis of a denial-of-service attack on TCP/IP (Synkill).

# Software development

Programming language experience: C, Perl, C++, Java, AWK, Unix shells (Bourne, C shell, Korn shell), Python, PHP, Ruby, Objective C, Cocoa (MacOS X).

Other experience: VMware VMsafe virtual machine introspection API, XML and related technologies, network programming, database programming (SQL), kernel programming (OpenBSD and Linux), HTML.

Major publicly-available software projects: CopperExport, mailer, AAFID<sub>2</sub> prototype

Other software projects (not publicly available): Pilatus, SOC in a Box, Billy Goat, Embedded Sensors Project (ESP).

# System administration experience

Unix systems: Linux, OpenBSD, FreeBSD, MacOS X, MacOS X Server, Solaris.

Configuration management: CFEngine 3.

Virtualization and cloud platforms: VMware ESX server 3.5-4.0, Xen 3.x, User Mode Linux, KVM, Amazon EC2.

Security systems and software: Snort IDS, Bro IDS, Nessus vulnerability scanner, HoneyNet platform, Nepenthes malware collection platform.

### Other professional activities (sample)

2011–2013: Member of the Editorial Board for the Computers & Security Journal.

2010–2012: Member of the Cfengine Champions (C<sup>3</sup>) program, which recognizes outstanding contribu-

tions to the CFEngine community.

2007–2012: Member of the Steering Committee for the International Symposium on Recent Advances in

Intrusion Detection (RAID).

2009: Program chair for the 2009 workshop of the Zurich Information Security Center (ZISC).

2008: Program chair for the SIG SIDAR Conference on Detection of Intrusions and Malware & Vul-

nerability Assessment (DIMVA).

2006: Program chair for the 9th International Symposium on Recent Advances in Intrusion Detec-

tion (RAID).

# Spoken languages

Spanish (native), English (near-native spoken and written fluency), German (basic), French (basic).

**References** Available by request.